<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<artist>
<filename>aidan_oliver</filename>
<name>Aidan Oliver</name>
<part>Musical Director</part>
<sex>male</sex>
<url>http://www.theorganmag.com/news/news-25-spiritus.html</url>

<cv>
<p>Aidan Oliver began his musical career as a chorister at Westminster Cathedral. 
As a treble soloist he appeared in concerts and recordings with groups including 
the King's Consort, the Corydon Singers, the BBC Concert Orchestra, and the 
Chicago Symphony Orchestra under Sir Georg Solti. After attending Eton 
College as a music scholar, he won a choral scholarship to King's College 
Cambridge, where he sang with the choir in numerous tours and recordings; 
he also directed the choral scholars' own group, Collegium Regale. 
After graduating with a Double First in Classics, Aidan continued 
both his academic and performing activities, first as a Kennedy Scholar 
at Harvard University, and then at King's College London where he 
completed an M.A. in musicology.</p>

<p>Aidan now works as a freelance conductor, singer and repetiteur. 
In 2001 he assisted Richard Hickox at the Spoleto Festival in Italy, 
working on a production of Gian Carlo Menotti's <work>The Saint of Bleecker 
Street</work>, directed by the 90-year-old composer himself. Earlier this year 
he worked as Assistant Conductor with Opera North on a highly acclaimed 
production of Britten's <work>Albert Herring</work> with a cast including Dame 
Josephine Barstow and John Graham Hall; he is currently working on 
Ravel <work>L'Enfant et les Sortilèges</work> with the same company. This summer 
he joined Garsington Opera as a repetiteur, assisting Elgar Howarth 
on a double bill of Jana&#x010d;ek operas.
Since October 2002 he has been studying as a répétiteur at the National Opera Studio.
</p>

<p delete="yes">Aidan is the founder and musical director of Spiritus, a professional 
chamber choir comprising some of the finest young singers in London. 
Since its debut in December 2000, Spiritus has performed to great 
acclaim in venues including the Temple Church, London, Jesus College 
Chapel in Cambridge, and the National Portrait Gallery. The group's 
repertoire includes both well-known and rarely performed masterpieces: 
the choir gave the second-ever UK performance of John Tavener's 
virtuosic <work>Innocence</work> in 2000, and recently revived an outstanding 
collection of partsongs written in honour of Queen Victoria's 80th birthday.</p>

<p>As well as taking up the directorship of 
 Wokingham Choral Society this year, Aidan was recently appointed as 
 Director of Music at St Margaret's Westminster, the 
 Parliamentary Church which stands next to Westminster Abbey. 
  This year he was awarded a Winston Churchill Travelling Fellowship 
 to study choral music in Russia, and in 2003 he will be taking up a 
 prestigious Conducting Fellowship with the BBC Singers.  
 He also sings regularly as a deputy with cathedral choirs 
 including Westminster Abbey and Westminster Cathedral.</p>

<p delete="yes">Aidan is also in demand as a consort singer, performing with groups 
including the Oxford Camerata and the Sarum Consort, with whom he has 
made several acclaimed recordings on the ASV label of motets by Bach 
and Peter Philips sung by solo voices.</p>

<p>Aidan has recently been awarded a Winston Churchill Memorial 
Travelling Fellowship to travel to Russia to study the Orthodox 
choral music and its performance.</p>



</cv>
<last-updated>October 2002</last-updated>
</artist> 

