<SCENE><TITLE> III.  Woods and cave, near the seashore.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter TIMON, from the cave</STAGEDIR>

<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O blessed breeding sun, draw from the earth</LINE>
<LINE>Rotten humidity; below thy sister's orb</LINE>
<LINE>Infect the air! Twinn'd brothers of one womb,</LINE>
<LINE>Whose procreation, residence, and birth,</LINE>
<LINE>Scarce is dividant, touch them with several fortunes;</LINE>
<LINE>The greater scorns the lesser: not nature,</LINE>
<LINE>To whom all sores lay siege, can bear great fortune,</LINE>
<LINE>But by contempt of nature.</LINE>
<LINE>Raise me this beggar, and deny 't that lord;</LINE>
<LINE>The senator shall bear contempt hereditary,</LINE>
<LINE>The beggar native honour.</LINE>
<LINE>It is the pasture lards the rother's sides,</LINE>
<LINE>The want that makes him lean. Who dares, who dares,</LINE>
<LINE>In purity of manhood stand upright,</LINE>
<LINE>And say 'This man's a flatterer?' if one be,</LINE>
<LINE>So are they all; for every grise of fortune</LINE>
<LINE>Is smooth'd by that below: the learned pate</LINE>
<LINE>Ducks to the golden fool: all is oblique;</LINE>
<LINE>There's nothing level in our cursed natures,</LINE>
<LINE>But direct villany. Therefore, be abhorr'd</LINE>
<LINE>All feasts, societies, and throngs of men!</LINE>
<LINE>His semblable, yea, himself, Timon disdains:</LINE>
<LINE>Destruction fang mankind! Earth, yield me roots!</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Digging</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Who seeks for better of thee, sauce his palate</LINE>
<LINE>With thy most operant poison! What is here?</LINE>
<LINE>Gold? yellow, glittering, precious gold? No, gods,</LINE>
<LINE>I am no idle votarist: roots, you clear heavens!</LINE>
<LINE>Thus much of this will make black white, foul fair,</LINE>
<LINE>Wrong right, base noble, old young, coward valiant.</LINE>
<LINE>Ha, you gods! why this? what this, you gods? Why, this</LINE>
<LINE>Will lug your priests and servants from your sides,</LINE>
<LINE>Pluck stout men's pillows from below their heads:</LINE>
<LINE>This yellow slave</LINE>
<LINE>Will knit and break religions, bless the accursed,</LINE>
<LINE>Make the hoar leprosy adored, place thieves</LINE>
<LINE>And give them title, knee and approbation</LINE>
<LINE>With senators on the bench: this is it</LINE>
<LINE>That makes the wappen'd widow wed again;</LINE>
<LINE>She, whom the spital-house and ulcerous sores</LINE>
<LINE>Would cast the gorge at, this embalms and spices</LINE>
<LINE>To the April day again. Come, damned earth,</LINE>
<LINE>Thou common whore of mankind, that put'st odds</LINE>
<LINE>Among the route of nations, I will make thee</LINE>
<LINE>Do thy right nature.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>March afar off</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Ha! a drum? Thou'rt quick,</LINE>
<LINE>But yet I'll bury thee: thou'lt go, strong thief,</LINE>
<LINE>When gouty keepers of thee cannot stand.</LINE>
<LINE>Nay, stay thou out for earnest.</LINE>

<STAGEDIR>Keeping some gold</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>Enter ALCIBIADES, with drum and fife, in
warlike manner; PHRYNIA and TIMANDRA</STAGEDIR>


<SPEAKER>ALCIBIADES</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What art thou there? speak.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A beast, as thou art. The canker gnaw thy heart,</LINE>
<LINE>For showing me again the eyes of man!</LINE>



<SPEAKER>ALCIBIADES</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What is thy name? Is man so hateful to thee,</LINE>
<LINE>That art thyself a man?</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am Misanthropos, and hate mankind.</LINE>
<LINE>For thy part, I do wish thou wert a dog,</LINE>
<LINE>That I might love thee something.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>ALCIBIADES</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I know thee well;</LINE>
<LINE>But in thy fortunes am unlearn'd and strange.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I know thee too; and more than that I know thee,</LINE>
<LINE>I not desire to know. Follow thy drum;</LINE>
<LINE>With man's blood paint the ground, gules, gules:</LINE>
<LINE>Religious canons, civil laws are cruel;</LINE>
<LINE>Then what should war be? This fell whore of thine</LINE>
<LINE>Hath in her more destruction than thy sword,</LINE>
<LINE>For all her cherubim look.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>PHRYNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thy lips rot off!</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will not kiss thee; then the rot returns</LINE>
<LINE>To thine own lips again.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>ALCIBIADES</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How came the noble Timon to this change?</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>As the moon does, by wanting light to give:</LINE>
<LINE>But then renew I could not, like the moon;</LINE>
<LINE>There were no suns to borrow of.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>ALCIBIADES</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Noble Timon,</LINE>
<LINE>What friendship may I do thee?</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>None, but to</LINE>
<LINE>Maintain my opinion.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>ALCIBIADES</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What is it, Timon?</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Promise me friendship, but perform none: if thou</LINE>
<LINE>wilt not promise, the gods plague thee, for thou art</LINE>
<LINE>a man! if thou dost perform, confound thee, for</LINE>
<LINE>thou art a man!</LINE>



<SPEAKER>ALCIBIADES</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have heard in some sort of thy miseries.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thou saw'st them, when I had prosperity.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>ALCIBIADES</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I see them now; then was a blessed time.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>As thine is now, held with a brace of harlots.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMANDRA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Is this the Athenian minion, whom the world</LINE>
<LINE>Voiced so regardfully?</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Art thou Timandra?</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMANDRA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yes.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Be a whore still: they love thee not that use thee;</LINE>
<LINE>Give them diseases, leaving with thee their lust.</LINE>
<LINE>Make use of thy salt hours: season the slaves</LINE>
<LINE>For tubs and baths; bring down rose-cheeked youth</LINE>
<LINE>To the tub-fast and the diet.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMANDRA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hang thee, monster!</LINE>



<SPEAKER>ALCIBIADES</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pardon him, sweet Timandra; for his wits</LINE>
<LINE>Are drown'd and lost in his calamities.</LINE>
<LINE>I have but little gold of late, brave Timon,</LINE>
<LINE>The want whereof doth daily make revolt</LINE>
<LINE>In my penurious band: I have heard, and grieved,</LINE>
<LINE>How cursed Athens, mindless of thy worth,</LINE>
<LINE>Forgetting thy great deeds, when neighbour states,</LINE>
<LINE>But for thy sword and fortune, trod upon them,--</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I prithee, beat thy drum, and get thee gone.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>ALCIBIADES</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am thy friend, and pity thee, dear Timon.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How dost thou pity him whom thou dost trouble?</LINE>
<LINE>I had rather be alone.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>ALCIBIADES</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, fare thee well:</LINE>
<LINE>Here is some gold for thee.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Keep it, I cannot eat it.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>ALCIBIADES</SPEAKER>
<LINE>When I have laid proud Athens on a heap,--</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Warr'st thou 'gainst Athens?</LINE>



<SPEAKER>ALCIBIADES</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, Timon, and have cause.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The gods confound them all in thy conquest;</LINE>
<LINE>And thee after, when thou hast conquer'd!</LINE>



<SPEAKER>ALCIBIADES</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why me, Timon?</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That, by killing of villains,</LINE>
<LINE>Thou wast born to conquer my country.</LINE>
<LINE>Put up thy gold: go on,--here's gold,--go on;</LINE>
<LINE>Be as a planetary plague, when Jove</LINE>
<LINE>Will o'er some high-viced city hang his poison</LINE>
<LINE>In the sick air: let not thy sword skip one:</LINE>
<LINE>Pity not honour'd age for his white beard;</LINE>
<LINE>He is an usurer: strike me the counterfeit matron;</LINE>
<LINE>It is her habit only that is honest,</LINE>
<LINE>Herself's a bawd: let not the virgin's cheek</LINE>
<LINE>Make soft thy trenchant sword; for those milk-paps,</LINE>
<LINE>That through the window-bars bore at men's eyes,</LINE>
<LINE>Are not within the leaf of pity writ,</LINE>
<LINE>But set them down horrible traitors: spare not the babe,</LINE>
<LINE>Whose dimpled smiles from fools exhaust their mercy;</LINE>
<LINE>Think it a bastard, whom the oracle</LINE>
<LINE>Hath doubtfully pronounced thy throat shall cut,</LINE>
<LINE>And mince it sans remorse: swear against objects;</LINE>
<LINE>Put armour on thine ears and on thine eyes;</LINE>
<LINE>Whose proof, nor yells of mothers, maids, nor babes,</LINE>
<LINE>Nor sight of priests in holy vestments bleeding,</LINE>
<LINE>Shall pierce a jot. There's gold to pay soldiers:</LINE>
<LINE>Make large confusion; and, thy fury spent,</LINE>
<LINE>Confounded be thyself! Speak not, be gone.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>ALCIBIADES</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hast thou gold yet? I'll take the gold thou</LINE>
<LINE>givest me,</LINE>
<LINE>Not all thy counsel.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Dost thou, or dost thou not, heaven's curse</LINE>
<LINE>upon thee!</LINE>



<SPEAKER>PHRYNIA</SPEAKER>
<SPEAKER>TIMANDRA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Give us some gold, good Timon: hast thou more?</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Enough to make a whore forswear her trade,</LINE>
<LINE>And to make whores, a bawd. Hold up, you sluts,</LINE>
<LINE>Your aprons mountant: you are not oathable,</LINE>
<LINE>Although, I know, you 'll swear, terribly swear</LINE>
<LINE>Into strong shudders and to heavenly agues</LINE>
<LINE>The immortal gods that hear you,--spare your oaths,</LINE>
<LINE>I'll trust to your conditions: be whores still;</LINE>
<LINE>And he whose pious breath seeks to convert you,</LINE>
<LINE>Be strong in whore, allure him, burn him up;</LINE>
<LINE>Let your close fire predominate his smoke,</LINE>
<LINE>And be no turncoats: yet may your pains, six months,</LINE>
<LINE>Be quite contrary: and thatch your poor thin roofs</LINE>
<LINE>With burthens of the dead;--some that were hang'd,</LINE>
<LINE>No matter:--wear them, betray with them: whore still;</LINE>
<LINE>Paint till a horse may mire upon your face,</LINE>
<LINE>A pox of wrinkles!</LINE>



<SPEAKER>PHRYNIA</SPEAKER>
<SPEAKER>TIMANDRA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, more gold: what then?</LINE>
<LINE>Believe't, that we'll do any thing for gold.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Consumptions sow</LINE>
<LINE>In hollow bones of man; strike their sharp shins,</LINE>
<LINE>And mar men's spurring. Crack the lawyer's voice,</LINE>
<LINE>That he may never more false title plead,</LINE>
<LINE>Nor sound his quillets shrilly: hoar the flamen,</LINE>
<LINE>That scolds against the quality of flesh,</LINE>
<LINE>And not believes himself: down with the nose,</LINE>
<LINE>Down with it flat; take the bridge quite away</LINE>
<LINE>Of him that, his particular to foresee,</LINE>
<LINE>Smells from the general weal: make curl'd-pate</LINE>
<LINE>ruffians bald;</LINE>
<LINE>And let the unscarr'd braggarts of the war</LINE>
<LINE>Derive some pain from you: plague all;</LINE>
<LINE>That your activity may defeat and quell</LINE>
<LINE>The source of all erection. There's more gold:</LINE>
<LINE>Do you damn others, and let this damn you,</LINE>
<LINE>And ditches grave you all!</LINE>



<SPEAKER>PHRYNIA</SPEAKER>
<SPEAKER>TIMANDRA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>More counsel with more money, bounteous Timon.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>More whore, more mischief first; I have given you earnest.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>ALCIBIADES</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Strike up the drum towards Athens! Farewell, Timon:</LINE>
<LINE>If I thrive well, I'll visit thee again.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If I hope well, I'll never see thee more.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>ALCIBIADES</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I never did thee harm.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yes, thou spokest well of me.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>ALCIBIADES</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Call'st thou that harm?</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Men daily find it. Get thee away, and take</LINE>
<LINE>Thy beagles with thee.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>ALCIBIADES</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We but offend him. Strike!</LINE>


<STAGEDIR>Drum beats. Exeunt ALCIBIADES, PHRYNIA,
and TIMANDRA</STAGEDIR>


<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That nature, being sick of man's unkindness,</LINE>
<LINE>Should yet be hungry! Common mother, thou,</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Digging</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Whose womb unmeasurable, and infinite breast,</LINE>
<LINE>Teems, and feeds all; whose self-same mettle,</LINE>
<LINE>Whereof thy proud child, arrogant man, is puff'd,</LINE>
<LINE>Engenders the black toad and adder blue,</LINE>
<LINE>The gilded newt and eyeless venom'd worm,</LINE>
<LINE>With all the abhorred births below crisp heaven</LINE>
<LINE>Whereon Hyperion's quickening fire doth shine;</LINE>
<LINE>Yield him, who all thy human sons doth hate,</LINE>
<LINE>From forth thy plenteous bosom, one poor root!</LINE>
<LINE>Ensear thy fertile and conceptious womb,</LINE>
<LINE>Let it no more bring out ingrateful man!</LINE>
<LINE>Go great with tigers, dragons, wolves, and bears;</LINE>
<LINE>Teem with new monsters, whom thy upward face</LINE>
<LINE>Hath to the marbled mansion all above</LINE>
<LINE>Never presented!--O, a root,--dear thanks!--</LINE>
<LINE>Dry up thy marrows, vines, and plough-torn leas;</LINE>
<LINE>Whereof ungrateful man, with liquorish draughts</LINE>
<LINE>And morsels unctuous, greases his pure mind,</LINE>
<LINE>That from it all consideration slips!</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter APEMANTUS</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>More man? plague, plague!</LINE>



<SPEAKER>APEMANTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I was directed hither: men report</LINE>
<LINE>Thou dost affect my manners, and dost use them.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis, then, because thou dost not keep a dog,</LINE>
<LINE>Whom I would imitate: consumption catch thee!</LINE>



<SPEAKER>APEMANTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This is in thee a nature but infected;</LINE>
<LINE>A poor unmanly melancholy sprung</LINE>
<LINE>From change of fortune. Why this spade? this place?</LINE>
<LINE>This slave-like habit? and these looks of care?</LINE>
<LINE>Thy flatterers yet wear silk, drink wine, lie soft;</LINE>
<LINE>Hug their diseased perfumes, and have forgot</LINE>
<LINE>That ever Timon was. Shame not these woods,</LINE>
<LINE>By putting on the cunning of a carper.</LINE>
<LINE>Be thou a flatterer now, and seek to thrive</LINE>
<LINE>By that which has undone thee: hinge thy knee,</LINE>
<LINE>And let his very breath, whom thou'lt observe,</LINE>
<LINE>Blow off thy cap; praise his most vicious strain,</LINE>
<LINE>And call it excellent: thou wast told thus;</LINE>
<LINE>Thou gavest thine ears like tapsters that bid welcome</LINE>
<LINE>To knaves and all approachers: 'tis most just</LINE>
<LINE>That thou turn rascal; hadst thou wealth again,</LINE>
<LINE>Rascals should have 't. Do not assume my likeness.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Were I like thee, I'ld throw away myself.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>APEMANTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thou hast cast away thyself, being like thyself;</LINE>
<LINE>A madman so long, now a fool. What, think'st</LINE>
<LINE>That the bleak air, thy boisterous chamberlain,</LINE>
<LINE>Will put thy shirt on warm? will these moss'd trees,</LINE>
<LINE>That have outlived the eagle, page thy heels,</LINE>
<LINE>And skip where thou point'st out? will the</LINE>
<LINE>cold brook,</LINE>
<LINE>Candied with ice, caudle thy morning taste,</LINE>
<LINE>To cure thy o'er-night's surfeit? Call the creatures</LINE>
<LINE>Whose naked natures live in an the spite</LINE>
<LINE>Of wreakful heaven, whose bare unhoused trunks,</LINE>
<LINE>To the conflicting elements exposed,</LINE>
<LINE>Answer mere nature; bid them flatter thee;</LINE>
<LINE>O, thou shalt find--</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A fool of thee: depart.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>APEMANTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I love thee better now than e'er I did.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I hate thee worse.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>APEMANTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why?</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thou flatter'st misery.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>APEMANTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I flatter not; but say thou art a caitiff.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why dost thou seek me out?</LINE>



<SPEAKER>APEMANTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To vex thee.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Always a villain's office or a fool's.</LINE>
<LINE>Dost please thyself in't?</LINE>



<SPEAKER>APEMANTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What! a knave too?</LINE>



<SPEAKER>APEMANTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If thou didst put this sour-cold habit on</LINE>
<LINE>To castigate thy pride, 'twere well: but thou</LINE>
<LINE>Dost it enforcedly; thou'ldst courtier be again,</LINE>
<LINE>Wert thou not beggar. Willing misery</LINE>
<LINE>Outlives encertain pomp, is crown'd before:</LINE>
<LINE>The one is filling still, never complete;</LINE>
<LINE>The other, at high wish: best state, contentless,</LINE>
<LINE>Hath a distracted and most wretched being,</LINE>
<LINE>Worse than the worst, content.</LINE>
<LINE>Thou shouldst desire to die, being miserable.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Not by his breath that is more miserable.</LINE>
<LINE>Thou art a slave, whom Fortune's tender arm</LINE>
<LINE>With favour never clasp'd; but bred a dog.</LINE>
<LINE>Hadst thou, like us from our first swath, proceeded</LINE>
<LINE>The sweet degrees that this brief world affords</LINE>
<LINE>To such as may the passive drugs of it</LINE>
<LINE>Freely command, thou wouldst have plunged thyself</LINE>
<LINE>In general riot; melted down thy youth</LINE>
<LINE>In different beds of lust; and never learn'd</LINE>
<LINE>The icy precepts of respect, but follow'd</LINE>
<LINE>The sugar'd game before thee. But myself,</LINE>
<LINE>Who had the world as my confectionary,</LINE>
<LINE>The mouths, the tongues, the eyes and hearts of men</LINE>
<LINE>At duty, more than I could frame employment,</LINE>
<LINE>That numberless upon me stuck as leaves</LINE>
<LINE>Do on the oak, hive with one winter's brush</LINE>
<LINE>Fell from their boughs and left me open, bare</LINE>
<LINE>For every storm that blows: I, to bear this,</LINE>
<LINE>That never knew but better, is some burden:</LINE>
<LINE>Thy nature did commence in sufferance, time</LINE>
<LINE>Hath made thee hard in't. Why shouldst thou hate men?</LINE>
<LINE>They never flatter'd thee: what hast thou given?</LINE>
<LINE>If thou wilt curse, thy father, that poor rag,</LINE>
<LINE>Must be thy subject, who in spite put stuff</LINE>
<LINE>To some she beggar and compounded thee</LINE>
<LINE>Poor rogue hereditary. Hence, be gone!</LINE>
<LINE>If thou hadst not been born the worst of men,</LINE>
<LINE>Thou hadst been a knave and flatterer.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>APEMANTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Art thou proud yet?</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, that I am not thee.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>APEMANTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I, that I was</LINE>
<LINE>No prodigal.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I, that I am one now:</LINE>
<LINE>Were all the wealth I have shut up in thee,</LINE>
<LINE>I'ld give thee leave to hang it. Get thee gone.</LINE>
<LINE>That the whole life of Athens were in this!</LINE>
<LINE>Thus would I eat it.</LINE>


<STAGEDIR>Eating a root</STAGEDIR>


<SPEAKER>APEMANTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Here; I will mend thy feast.</LINE>


<STAGEDIR>Offering him a root</STAGEDIR>


<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>First mend my company, take away thyself.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>APEMANTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So I shall mend mine own, by the lack of thine.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis not well mended so, it is but botch'd;</LINE>
<LINE>if not, I would it were.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>APEMANTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What wouldst thou have to Athens?</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thee thither in a whirlwind. If thou wilt,</LINE>
<LINE>Tell them there I have gold; look, so I have.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>APEMANTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Here is no use for gold.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The best and truest;</LINE>
<LINE>For here it sleeps, and does no hired harm.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>APEMANTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Where liest o' nights, Timon?</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Under that's above me.</LINE>
<LINE>Where feed'st thou o' days, Apemantus?</LINE>



<SPEAKER>APEMANTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Where my stomach finds meat; or, rather, where I eat</LINE>
<LINE>it.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Would poison were obedient and knew my mind!</LINE>



<SPEAKER>APEMANTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Where wouldst thou send it?</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To sauce thy dishes.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>APEMANTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The middle of humanity thou never knewest, but the</LINE>
<LINE>extremity of both ends: when thou wast in thy gilt</LINE>
<LINE>and thy perfume, they mocked thee for too much</LINE>
<LINE>curiosity; in thy rags thou knowest none, but art</LINE>
<LINE>despised for the contrary. There's a medlar for</LINE>
<LINE>thee, eat it.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>On what I hate I feed not.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>APEMANTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Dost hate a medlar?</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, though it look like thee.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>APEMANTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>An thou hadst hated meddlers sooner, thou shouldst</LINE>
<LINE>have loved thyself better now. What man didst thou</LINE>
<LINE>ever know unthrift that was beloved after his means?</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Who, without those means thou talkest of, didst thou</LINE>
<LINE>ever know beloved?</LINE>



<SPEAKER>APEMANTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Myself.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I understand thee; thou hadst some means to keep a</LINE>
<LINE>dog.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>APEMANTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What things in the world canst thou nearest compare</LINE>
<LINE>to thy flatterers?</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Women nearest; but men, men are the things</LINE>
<LINE>themselves. What wouldst thou do with the world,</LINE>
<LINE>Apemantus, if it lay in thy power?</LINE>



<SPEAKER>APEMANTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Give it the beasts, to be rid of the men.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Wouldst thou have thyself fall in the confusion of</LINE>
<LINE>men, and remain a beast with the beasts?</LINE>



<SPEAKER>APEMANTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, Timon.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A beastly ambition, which the gods grant thee t'</LINE>
<LINE>attain to! If thou wert the lion, the fox would</LINE>
<LINE>beguile thee; if thou wert the lamb, the fox would</LINE>
<LINE>eat three: if thou wert the fox, the lion would</LINE>
<LINE>suspect thee, when peradventure thou wert accused by</LINE>
<LINE>the ass: if thou wert the ass, thy dulness would</LINE>
<LINE>torment thee, and still thou livedst but as a</LINE>
<LINE>breakfast to the wolf: if thou wert the wolf, thy</LINE>
<LINE>greediness would afflict thee, and oft thou shouldst</LINE>
<LINE>hazard thy life for thy dinner: wert thou the</LINE>
<LINE>unicorn, pride and wrath would confound thee and</LINE>
<LINE>make thine own self the conquest of thy fury: wert</LINE>
<LINE>thou a bear, thou wouldst be killed by the horse:</LINE>
<LINE>wert thou a horse, thou wouldst be seized by the</LINE>
<LINE>leopard: wert thou a leopard, thou wert german to</LINE>
<LINE>the lion and the spots of thy kindred were jurors on</LINE>
<LINE>thy life: all thy safety were remotion and thy</LINE>
<LINE>defence absence. What beast couldst thou be, that</LINE>
<LINE>were not subject to a beast? and what a beast art</LINE>
<LINE>thou already, that seest not thy loss in</LINE>
<LINE>transformation!</LINE>



<SPEAKER>APEMANTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If thou couldst please me with speaking to me, thou</LINE>
<LINE>mightst have hit upon it here: the commonwealth of</LINE>
<LINE>Athens is become a forest of beasts.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How has the ass broke the wall, that thou art out of the city?</LINE>



<SPEAKER>APEMANTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yonder comes a poet and a painter: the plague of</LINE>
<LINE>company light upon thee! I will fear to catch it</LINE>
<LINE>and give way: when I know not what else to do, I'll</LINE>
<LINE>see thee again.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>When there is nothing living but thee, thou shalt be</LINE>
<LINE>welcome. I had rather be a beggar's dog than Apemantus.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>APEMANTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thou art the cap of all the fools alive.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Would thou wert clean enough to spit upon!</LINE>



<SPEAKER>APEMANTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A plague on thee! thou art too bad to curse.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>All villains that do stand by thee are pure.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>APEMANTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>There is no leprosy but what thou speak'st.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If I name thee.</LINE>
<LINE>I'll beat thee, but I should infect my hands.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>APEMANTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I would my tongue could rot them off!</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Away, thou issue of a mangy dog!</LINE>
<LINE>Choler does kill me that thou art alive;</LINE>
<LINE>I swound to see thee.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>APEMANTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Would thou wouldst burst!</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Away,</LINE>
<LINE>Thou tedious rogue! I am sorry I shall lose</LINE>
<LINE>A stone by thee.</LINE>


<STAGEDIR>Throws a stone at him</STAGEDIR>


<SPEAKER>APEMANTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Beast!</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Slave!</LINE>



<SPEAKER>APEMANTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Toad!</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Rogue, rogue, rogue!</LINE>
<LINE>I am sick of this false world, and will love nought</LINE>
<LINE>But even the mere necessities upon 't.</LINE>
<LINE>Then, Timon, presently prepare thy grave;</LINE>
<LINE>Lie where the light foam the sea may beat</LINE>
<LINE>Thy grave-stone daily: make thine epitaph,</LINE>
<LINE>That death in me at others' lives may laugh.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>To the gold</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>O thou sweet king-killer, and dear divorce</LINE>
<LINE>'Twixt natural son and sire! thou bright defiler</LINE>
<LINE>Of Hymen's purest bed! thou valiant Mars!</LINE>
<LINE>Thou ever young, fresh, loved and delicate wooer,</LINE>
<LINE>Whose blush doth thaw the consecrated snow</LINE>
<LINE>That lies on Dian's lap! thou visible god,</LINE>
<LINE>That solder'st close impossibilities,</LINE>
<LINE>And makest them kiss! that speak'st with</LINE>
<LINE>every tongue,</LINE>
<LINE>To every purpose! O thou touch of hearts!</LINE>
<LINE>Think, thy slave man rebels, and by thy virtue</LINE>
<LINE>Set them into confounding odds, that beasts</LINE>
<LINE>May have the world in empire!</LINE>



<SPEAKER>APEMANTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Would 'twere so!</LINE>
<LINE>But not till I am dead. I'll say thou'st gold:</LINE>
<LINE>Thou wilt be throng'd to shortly.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Throng'd to!</LINE>



<SPEAKER>APEMANTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thy back, I prithee.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>APEMANTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Live, and love thy misery.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Long live so, and so die.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exit APEMANTUS</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>I am quit.</LINE>
<LINE>Moe things like men! Eat, Timon, and abhor them.</LINE>


<STAGEDIR>Enter Banditti</STAGEDIR>


<SPEAKER>First Bandit</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Where should he have this gold? It is some poor</LINE>
<LINE>fragment, some slender sort of his remainder: the</LINE>
<LINE>mere want of gold, and the falling-from of his</LINE>
<LINE>friends, drove him into this melancholy.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>Second Bandit</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is noised he hath a mass of treasure.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>Third Bandit</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let us make the assay upon him: if he care not</LINE>
<LINE>for't, he will supply us easily; if he covetously</LINE>
<LINE>reserve it, how shall's get it?</LINE>



<SPEAKER>Second Bandit</SPEAKER>
<LINE>True; for he bears it not about him, 'tis hid.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>First Bandit</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Is not this he?</LINE>



<SPEAKER>Banditti</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Where?</LINE>



<SPEAKER>Second Bandit</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis his description.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>Third Bandit</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He; I know him.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>Banditti</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Save thee, Timon.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now, thieves?</LINE>



<SPEAKER>Banditti</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Soldiers, not thieves.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Both too; and women's sons.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>Banditti</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We are not thieves, but men that much do want.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Your greatest want is, you want much of meat.</LINE>
<LINE>Why should you want? Behold, the earth hath roots;</LINE>
<LINE>Within this mile break forth a hundred springs;</LINE>
<LINE>The oaks bear mast, the briers scarlet hips;</LINE>
<LINE>The bounteous housewife, nature, on each bush</LINE>
<LINE>Lays her full mess before you. Want! why want?</LINE>



<SPEAKER>First Bandit</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We cannot live on grass, on berries, water,</LINE>
<LINE>As beasts and birds and fishes.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nor on the beasts themselves, the birds, and fishes;</LINE>
<LINE>You must eat men. Yet thanks I must you con</LINE>
<LINE>That you are thieves profess'd, that you work not</LINE>
<LINE>In holier shapes: for there is boundless theft</LINE>
<LINE>In limited professions. Rascal thieves,</LINE>
<LINE>Here's gold. Go, suck the subtle blood o' the grape,</LINE>
<LINE>Till the high fever seethe your blood to froth,</LINE>
<LINE>And so 'scape hanging: trust not the physician;</LINE>
<LINE>His antidotes are poison, and he slays</LINE>
<LINE>Moe than you rob: take wealth and lives together;</LINE>
<LINE>Do villany, do, since you protest to do't,</LINE>
<LINE>Like workmen. I'll example you with thievery.</LINE>
<LINE>The sun's a thief, and with his great attraction</LINE>
<LINE>Robs the vast sea: the moon's an arrant thief,</LINE>
<LINE>And her pale fire she snatches from the sun:</LINE>
<LINE>The sea's a thief, whose liquid surge resolves</LINE>
<LINE>The moon into salt tears: the earth's a thief,</LINE>
<LINE>That feeds and breeds by a composture stolen</LINE>
<LINE>From general excrement: each thing's a thief:</LINE>
<LINE>The laws, your curb and whip, in their rough power</LINE>
<LINE>Have uncheque'd theft. Love not yourselves: away,</LINE>
<LINE>Rob one another. There's more gold. Cut throats:</LINE>
<LINE>All that you meet are thieves: to Athens go,</LINE>
<LINE>Break open shops; nothing can you steal,</LINE>
<LINE>But thieves do lose it: steal no less for this</LINE>
<LINE>I give you; and gold confound you howsoe'er! Amen.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>Third Bandit</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Has almost charmed me from my profession, by</LINE>
<LINE>persuading me to it.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>First Bandit</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis in the malice of mankind that he thus advises</LINE>
<LINE>us; not to have us thrive in our mystery.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>Second Bandit</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I'll believe him as an enemy, and give over my trade.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>First Bandit</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let us first see peace in Athens: there is no time</LINE>
<LINE>so miserable but a man may be true.</LINE>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt Banditti</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>Enter FLAVIUS</STAGEDIR>


<SPEAKER>FLAVIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O you gods!</LINE>
<LINE>Is yond despised and ruinous man my lord?</LINE>
<LINE>Full of decay and failing? O monument</LINE>
<LINE>And wonder of good deeds evilly bestow'd!</LINE>
<LINE>What an alteration of honour</LINE>
<LINE>Has desperate want made!</LINE>
<LINE>What viler thing upon the earth than friends</LINE>
<LINE>Who can bring noblest minds to basest ends!</LINE>
<LINE>How rarely does it meet with this time's guise,</LINE>
<LINE>When man was wish'd to love his enemies!</LINE>
<LINE>Grant I may ever love, and rather woo</LINE>
<LINE>Those that would mischief me than those that do!</LINE>
<LINE>Has caught me in his eye: I will present</LINE>
<LINE>My honest grief unto him; and, as my lord,</LINE>
<LINE>Still serve him with my life. My dearest master!</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Away! what art thou?</LINE>



<SPEAKER>FLAVIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Have you forgot me, sir?</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why dost ask that? I have forgot all men;</LINE>
<LINE>Then, if thou grant'st thou'rt a man, I have forgot thee.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>FLAVIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>An honest poor servant of yours.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Then I know thee not:</LINE>
<LINE>I never had honest man about me, I; all</LINE>
<LINE>I kept were knaves, to serve in meat to villains.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>FLAVIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The gods are witness,</LINE>
<LINE>Ne'er did poor steward wear a truer grief</LINE>
<LINE>For his undone lord than mine eyes for you.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What, dost thou weep? Come nearer. Then I</LINE>
<LINE>love thee,</LINE>
<LINE>Because thou art a woman, and disclaim'st</LINE>
<LINE>Flinty mankind; whose eyes do never give</LINE>
<LINE>But thorough lust and laughter. Pity's sleeping:</LINE>
<LINE>Strange times, that weep with laughing, not with weeping!</LINE>



<SPEAKER>FLAVIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I beg of you to know me, good my lord,</LINE>
<LINE>To accept my grief and whilst this poor wealth lasts</LINE>
<LINE>To entertain me as your steward still.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Had I a steward</LINE>
<LINE>So true, so just, and now so comfortable?</LINE>
<LINE>It almost turns my dangerous nature mild.</LINE>
<LINE>Let me behold thy face. Surely, this man</LINE>
<LINE>Was born of woman.</LINE>
<LINE>Forgive my general and exceptless rashness,</LINE>
<LINE>You perpetual-sober gods! I do proclaim</LINE>
<LINE>One honest man--mistake me not--but one;</LINE>
<LINE>No more, I pray,--and he's a steward.</LINE>
<LINE>How fain would I have hated all mankind!</LINE>
<LINE>And thou redeem'st thyself: but all, save thee,</LINE>
<LINE>I fell with curses.</LINE>
<LINE>Methinks thou art more honest now than wise;</LINE>
<LINE>For, by oppressing and betraying me,</LINE>
<LINE>Thou mightst have sooner got another service:</LINE>
<LINE>For many so arrive at second masters,</LINE>
<LINE>Upon their first lord's neck. But tell me true--</LINE>
<LINE>For I must ever doubt, though ne'er so sure--</LINE>
<LINE>Is not thy kindness subtle, covetous,</LINE>
<LINE>If not a usuring kindness, and, as rich men deal gifts,</LINE>
<LINE>Expecting in return twenty for one?</LINE>



<SPEAKER>FLAVIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, my most worthy master; in whose breast</LINE>
<LINE>Doubt and suspect, alas, are placed too late:</LINE>
<LINE>You should have fear'd false times when you did feast:</LINE>
<LINE>Suspect still comes where an estate is least.</LINE>
<LINE>That which I show, heaven knows, is merely love,</LINE>
<LINE>Duty and zeal to your unmatched mind,</LINE>
<LINE>Care of your food and living; and, believe it,</LINE>
<LINE>My most honour'd lord,</LINE>
<LINE>For any benefit that points to me,</LINE>
<LINE>Either in hope or present, I'ld exchange</LINE>
<LINE>For this one wish, that you had power and wealth</LINE>
<LINE>To requite me, by making rich yourself.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Look thee, 'tis so! Thou singly honest man,</LINE>
<LINE>Here, take: the gods out of my misery</LINE>
<LINE>Have sent thee treasure. Go, live rich and happy;</LINE>
<LINE>But thus condition'd: thou shalt build from men;</LINE>
<LINE>Hate all, curse all, show charity to none,</LINE>
<LINE>But let the famish'd flesh slide from the bone,</LINE>
<LINE>Ere thou relieve the beggar; give to dogs</LINE>
<LINE>What thou deny'st to men; let prisons swallow 'em,</LINE>
<LINE>Debts wither 'em to nothing; be men like</LINE>
<LINE>blasted woods,</LINE>
<LINE>And may diseases lick up their false bloods!</LINE>
<LINE>And so farewell and thrive.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>FLAVIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, let me stay,</LINE>
<LINE>And comfort you, my master.</LINE>



<SPEAKER>TIMON</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If thou hatest curses,</LINE>
<LINE>Stay not; fly, whilst thou art blest and free:</LINE>
<LINE>Ne'er see thou man, and let me ne'er see thee.</LINE>


<STAGEDIR>Exit FLAVIUS. TIMON retires to his cave</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

